Guide to the Wilson Compton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Wilson Martindale Compton papers
1924-1961
MS 1175
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Writings and speeches of Wilson M. Compton, relating to lumbering and logging, forest management, and housing construction; includes material prepared for the National Lumber Manufacturers Association.
Compton, Wilson Martindale, 1890-1967
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elwood Maunder, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists almost entirely of writings and speeches by Wilson Martindale Compton on the lumber and logging industry, on housing construction, and on forest management. Included are typescripts, some with extensive annotations, mimeographed reports, printed articles, and transcripts of Compton's testimony before various government agencies on unemployment in the lumber industry and similar topics. A number of the reports were prepared for the National Lumber Manufacturers Association, of which Compton was secretary and general manager from 1918 through 1944. Several memoranda and minutes of the National Lumber Manufacturers Association and of the American Forestry Association are interfiled with Compton's writings, which are arranged in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
Wilson Martindale Compton was born in Wooster, Ohio, on October 15, 1890. He attended Wooster College, receiving the degrees of Ph.B. in 1911, M.A. in 1912, and LL.D. in 1935. He also received a Ph.D. from Princeton in 1915. Compton was a fellow at Princeton between 1913 and 1915. He was appointed assistant professor at Dartmouth between 1915 and 1916. Between 1916 and 1918, he was an economist with the Federal Trade Commission. The majority of his working career, however, was spent as secretary and general manager at National Lumber Manufacturers Association, where he worked from 1918 until 1944. Between 1934 and 1941, he was also a professor at George Washington University. After leaving National Lumber, he was president of Washington State University and State Export Station. He was also a member and director of the Council of Financial Aid to Education., Inc., in New York City, between 1953 and 1967. He died on March 7, 1967.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forest management; Housing; Logging; Lumbering; Educators; Compton, Wilson Martindale, 1890-1967; National Lumber Manufacturers Association
- Inventory
  - Writings
    - 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)